
<p>269.        <Learning Objectives Transitions List></p>
~~^G^ Learned how to write high-level algorithms
~~^G^ Learned about various sorting algorithms 
~~^G^ Learned the importance of networking with others and making useful connections
~~^G^ Wrote elementary code in Small Basic##EndBull
<p>
<Learning Objectives List, 1.5-second interval></p>
<p>^G^ MODULE 7. Writing Code</p>
<p>^G^ Learning objectives: </p>
~~^G^ Assign variables
~~^G^ Perform math equations through coding
~~^G^ Write and execute conditional statements
~~^G^ Write and execute loops 
~~^G^ Utilize and customize the Graphics Window in Small Basics##EndBull

<p>^G^ SUBMODULE A. Variables and Equations          </p>
<p>
VARIABLES   <Template-blank & Note>

These things the computer is keeping track of are usually called “variables”. This is because the VALUE part of it can change when you tell the computer to change it. The fact that the value can vary is why it’s called a “variable” – its value is not permanent or constant.

Usually the “=” symbol is used to set the VALUE of a variable.

When the “=” symbol is used to set the value of a variable, it is usually used like this:
[NAME of the variable] = [VALUE that is being assigned to that variable]

EXAMPLE: fabricColor = “blue”.

Here, there is a piece of data that the computer is keeping track of that has been given the name “fabricColor”. By using the “=” symbol, we can set the value of the piece of data called “fabricColor”. In this case, we are setting that value to the series of letters “blue”. 

270.        <Template-blank & Transition List>

CHALLENGE:

Write a program that contains the following elements:

-A background color, 
-A foreground color, 
-The TextWindow.Pause() operation, and
-The WriteLine operation.

Note: You are being asked to use the TextWindow.Pause() operation which is something you haven’t learned on this course. As we mentioned earlier, you will occasionally be tasked with performing actions you haven’t been taught yet. This is intentional and is a vital component of the learning process. Remember to research online for solutions and data as needed.  

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:</p>
<p>
•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 

271.        <Template-blank>

MORE VARIABLES

Let’s make it so the program can store and print variables. 

Write and execute the following code:

TextWindow.Write("What is your favorite food?: ")
food = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.WriteLine("Your favorite food is " + food + "! Yummy!")
TextWindow.Write("Which city would you most like to visit?: ")
city = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.WriteLine(city + " sounds like a great place to visit! Don’t forget to bring your computer with you!")

Read() in your above code is an operation that instructs the computer to stand by for the user to type something and then press the Enter/Return key. After the user types in data and hits Enter/Return, the computer takes what they typed and returns it to the program. 

272.        <Template-blank & Note>

MORE VARIABLES

As covered earlier, a variable is a place where values are stored for later use. In your code, food and city are variables. The text the user types in response to food and city are stored in variables. The variable “food” was used to store the user’s favorite food, while the variable “city” was used to store the city that the user wished to visit. 

When naming a variable, it is recommended that you use a name that describes the variable. For example: user_address = TextWindow.Read() would be a good name for a variable that stores a user’s home address, whereas giraffe = TextWindow.Read() would not be a good name for storing user address data.

273.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Write a program that contains the following elements:
-The TextWindow.Write operation,
-The TextWindow.Read operation, and
-The CursorTop property (note: a property is an attribute of an object).

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 

274.        <Template-blank & Note>

MATH AND NUMBERS

You can also store and utilize numbers in variables and perform mathematical equations. 

Write and execute the following code:

First_number = 5
Second_number = 10
Third_number = 15
Fourth_number = 20
Fifth_number = 50
Sixth_number = 16
TextWindow.WriteLine(Second_number + Third_number)

We just added 10 and 15 together. 

The variable numbers have been assigned various values, as follows:

●        You assigned the variable First_number the value 5
●        You assigned the variable Second_number the value 10
●        You assigned the variable Third_number the value 15
●        You assigned the variable Fourth_number the value 20
●        You assigned the variable Fifth_number the value 50
●        You assigned the variable Sixth_number the value 16

When we used “text” as a parameter earlier, we were required to surround the text with quotation marks, but with numeric parameters, quotation marks are unnecessary. 

275.        <Template-blank & Note>

SUBTRACTION

You can also perform subtraction. Add the following code beneath your existing code and execute it:

TextWindow.WriteLine(25 - First_number)

276.        <Template-blank>

MULTIPLICATION

You can multiply numbers. Add the following code beneath your existing code and execute it:

TextWindow.WriteLine(20 * Fourth_number)

277.        <Template-blank & Note>

DIVISION

You can divide numbers as well. Add the following code beneath your existing code and execute it:

TextWindow.WriteLine(400 / Fifth_number)

278.        <Template-blank>

We can also get the square root of a number. Add the following code beneath your existing code and execute it:

TextWindow.WriteLine(Math.SquareRoot (Sixth_number))

To explain the code you just wrote: the "Math" code you used here is an example of a library. In computer programming, a "library" is a pre-made package of computer code. Libraries are useful in computer programming because it means the programmer doesn't have to write the code to do the functions that the library provides, he or she can just use the pre-made library.

“Math” is a library that’s built into Small Basic. SquareRoot is an operation available from the Math library. 

279.        <Template-blank>

Using the Math library, you can also round numbers. Add the following code beneath your existing code and execute it:

TextWindow.WriteLine(Math.Round(5.6))

Feel free to play around with your variables and different math operations.

280.        <Template-blank>

Another interesting thing you can do with Small Basic is convert temperature from Fahrenheit to Celsius. 

The way you convert Fahrenheit to Celsius is: Fahrenheit temperature subtracted by 32, multiplied by 5/9ths. Or written as an equation:
T(°C) = (T(°F) - 32) × 5/9

Add the following code beneath your existing code and execute it:

TextWindow.Write("What is temperature in Fahrenheit?: ")
Fahrenheit = TextWindow.ReadNumber()
Celsius = (Fahrenheit - 32) * 5/9
TextWindow.WriteLine("The temperature in Fahrenheit converted to Celsius is: " + Celsius)

281.        <Template-blank>

We can also write a short program that randomly provides the user with a number.

Write and execute the following code:

TextWindow.WriteLine(Math.GetRandomNumber(100))

282.        <Template-blank & Note>


CHALLENGE:

Write a program that includes the following:

-The TextWindow.Title property,
-Assigning a value to a variable,
-The TextWindow.WriteLine operation, and
-The TextWindow.Top property.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com </p>

<p>^G^ SUBMODULE B. Writing Conditional Statements </p>
<p>
283.        <Template-blank & Note>

CONDITIONAL STATEMENTS

A condition is something that other things depend on. In math, a condition is something that is required for something else to be true. Conditions are points that are necessary to be present for other points to be present.  If you say something is “conditional”, that means it relies on the state of another thing.

EXAMPLE: The statement “Electricity is allowed to flow through this part of the computer if you type 1” could be a condition. Or say you have a word problem like this: “Come up with two digits that, when added together, equal six – but the digits 2 and 4 are never to be used to get the answer.” Here, the part that tells you that you can’t use the numbers 2 or 4 in your answer is a condition.

A conditional statement takes place when you tell the computer: depending upon ___, do ___. An “If Statement” is a type of conditional statement that means: if this, then that. 

284.        <Template-blank & Note>

BRANCHES

A branch is a point of decision. Branches are a fundamental element of how we make computers do useful work. A branch instruction tells the computer to go to somewhere other than the primary series of instructions and instead execute an alternate series of instructions; usually based on some decision the computer has to make. It is a statement written in the program’s code to make the computer shift from one area to another.  

EXAMPLE: If you are using a computer program to order food from a restaurant, and the restaurant has a different procedure for ordering if you want the food to be delivered instead of being set aside for you to pick up, there will be a branch in the computer program where the user will be prompted as to whether their order is for pickup or delivery. In this case, the computer will have two series of steps it will perform. The branch instruction in the computer program will execute one or the other of these series, depending on the user’s response.

285.        <Template-blank & Note>

COMPARISON INSTRUCTIONS
0
In order to tell the computer how to analyze conditional statements, you'll make use of comparison instructions, such as the < and > symbols.

Write and execute the following code:

If (5 < 10) Then
 TextWindow.WriteLine("Five is less than 10.")
EndIf

The EndIf statement tells the computer that we are done with that operation. 

286.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Write and execute your own conditional statement.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 

287.        <Template-blank & Note>

MORE CONDITIONAL STATEMENTS

Now let’s try using an ElseIf Statement, which is basically a second If Statement and gives us another option to choose from. We will also use an Else Statement that tells the computer, “Otherwise, do ___.” You’ll get a better idea of this through trying it out.

Write and execute the following code:

start:
TextWindow.Write("Are you a vegan?: ")
Vegan = TextWindow.Read()
If Vegan = "Yes" Then 
 TextWindow.WriteLine("I know, you've told me already. Several times...")
ElseIf Vegan = "No" Then
 TextWindow.WriteLine("Looks like meat is back on the menu!")
Else
 TextWindow.WriteLine("Please enter Yes or No.")
 Goto start
EndIf

We also added a couple new things to your code above:

1.        Start:. This is called a label. It’s similar to a bookmark within your program. In this case, the start label defines the beginning of our code and gave us a place to return to in our program, and
2.        Goto: This is an instruction which makes the program go to an exact place in the series of instructions that make up the program. “Goto” statements utilize labels and redirect the program to a label. 

288.        <Template-blank & Note>

COMPARISON INSTRUCTIONS

Here is another comparison instruction:

>= (greater-than sign followed by equal sign). This symbol is used to show that a comparison should be made. Specifically, this "greater-than or equal" symbol is basically an instruction to check whether the data on the left side of the symbol is more than or equal in amount or quantity than the data on the right side. The answer to this comparison is an answer of "true" or "false".

EXAMPLE: 6 >= 6. This means “check whether 6 is greater than or equal to 6”. The answer is "true". 

289.        

TIME

Now let’s create a program that can tell the difference between a.m. and p.m. Write and execute the following code:

If (Clock.Hour < 12) Then
 TextWindow.WriteLine("It is a.m.")
ElseIf (Clock.Hour >= 12) Then
 TextWindow.WriteLine("It is p.m.")
EndIf

Clock.Hour is a built-in instruction in SmallBasic that gives the time on your computer; we used that to check the time.

290.        

TIME 
There is also another way you can write your code:

Write and execute the following code:

If (Clock.Hour < 12) Then
 TextWindow.WriteLine("It is a.m.")
 Else
   TextWindow.WriteLine("It is p.m.")
EndIf

As you can see, the code is sometimes automatically indented for you. This is so that the code is sectioned off and you can easily read through it. In Small Basic, this indentation isn’t necessary and the program will run whether or not the code is indented. 

291.        <Template-blank & Note>

REMAINDER

Now let’s use some of what we’ve learned so far (and learn some more) to build a program that will round numbers and tell us whether or not the numbers are odd or even.

In math, a “remainder” is the number left over after a division operation. Math.Remainder is an operation in Small Basic that divides the first number by the second and returns (gives back) the remainder. E.g. All even numbers will have a 0 remainder when divided by 2 (nothing left over – they divide evenly).

Write and execute the following code:

TextWindow.Write("Type a number that includes a decimal: ")
Number = TextWindow.ReadNumber()
TextWindow.Write("Now we will round your number! ...")
TextWindow.Write("Your rounded number is: " + Math.Round(Number) + ".")
Remainder = Math.Remainder(Math.Round(Number), 2)
If (Remainder = 0) Then
 TextWindow.WriteLine(" This number is even!")
 Else
   TextWindow.WriteLine(" This is an odd number!")
EndIf

292.        <Template-blank & Note>

PROGRAM DELAY

When running your last code, did you notice how the text all just blurted out? Let’s add a delay so that one sentence displays at a time. To do so we use the Program.Delay() operation. Within the parentheses after "Delay", you enter how many milliseconds you want to wait before the program continues. 

Write and execute the following code:

TextWindow.Write("Type a number that includes a decimal: ")
Number = TextWindow.ReadNumber()
Program.Delay(1000)
TextWindow.Write("Now we will round your number! ...")
Program.Delay(1000)
TextWindow.Write("Your rounded number is: " + Math.Round(Number) + ".")
Program.Delay(1000)
Remainder = Math.Remainder(Math.Round(Number), 2)
If (Remainder = 0) Then
 TextWindow.WriteLine(" This number is even!")
 Program.Delay(1000)
 Else
   TextWindow.WriteLine(" This is an odd number!")
   Program.Delay(1000)
EndIf

As a note: in our last program, the If Statement and the Else Statement are control statements while the code that is executed in response to those control statements are the branches. 

In our last program, the first branch is: 

TextWindow.WriteLine(" This number is even!")
Program.Delay(1000)

And the second branch is:

TextWindow.WriteLine(" This is an odd number!")
Program.Delay(1000)

293.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Write a program that includes the following:

-If statement, 
-ElseIf statement, 
-Else statement, 
-Program.delay, 
-Math.Remainder, and
-Math.Ceiling(number).

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 

294.        <Template-blank & Note>
</p>
<p>^G^ SUBMODULE C. Creating Loops</p>
<p>
LOOPS

As we covered earlier, a loop is something that connects back to the beginning point. In computers, a loop is a sequence of instructions that are continually repeated until an exact condition is achieved.

Usually a loop will occur when a certain set of actions are performed by a computer program. The program would then check to see if it has reached the condition required for completion. If not, it starts over and repeats the set of actions. If so, it exits the loop and moves on to the next consecutive instruction in the computer program.

EXAMPLE: You tell the computer to search through a list of paint colors until the color “red” is found.

The list that the computer will search is this:

Blue
Yellow
Red
Orange
White

A loop is written into the computer and looks something like this:

Step 1: Get next consecutive item in the list.
Step 2: Check whether the item equals "Red".
Step 3: If the item equals "Red", exit this loop.
Step 4: If the item is not equal to "Red", loop back to step 1.

When this loop is executed, it will go like this:
Step 1: Acquired "Blue"
Step 2: Checked if "Blue" equal to "Red"
Step 3: Item not equal to "Red". Did not exit the loop.
Step 4: Item not equal to "Red". Looped back to Step 1.
Step 1: Acquired "Yellow"
Step 2: Checked if "Yellow" equal to "Red"
Step 3: Item not equal to "Red". Did not exit the loop.
Step 4: Item not equal to "Red". Looped back to Step 1.
Step 1: Acquired "Red"
Step 2: Checked if "Red" equal to "Red"
Step 3: Item equal to "Red". Exited the loop.

295.        <Template-blank & Note>

WHILE AND FOR LOOPS

A couple of important types of loops are “While Loops” and “For Loops.” 

A “While Loop” is basically a repeating “if statement.” Meaning, you are telling the computer to execute certain code repeatedly while a particular condition is present. E.g. While hungry, eat. 
        
Write and execute the following code in the text Editor:

Amount = 1
While (Amount < 1025)
 TextWindow.WriteLine(Amount)  
 Amount = Amount * 2
EndWhile

In this program we are telling the program that “As long as the Amount is less than 1025, multiply the Amount by 2.”

296.        <Template-blank>

ITERATIONS

An important aspect of how loops work is the concept of an iteration.

To iterate means to say or do something again; to repeat something. An iteration is the act of repeating. Iteration means to go through a defined series of actions, repeating a certain number of times. Usually this defined series of actions is repeated a certain number of times, or until a condition is met.

EXAMPLE: Computer programs are usually created in iterations: Coming up with a basic working version, reviewing the program for mistakes to correct and improvements to make, doing that work, and repeating. When the program works acceptably, this process starts.

297.        <Template-blank & Note>

FOR LOOPS

A “For Loop” is used to repeat a section of code a number of times. For Loops are used when the number of iterations are known. Here’s an example: for each student in the class (25), provide a grade. 

Write and execute the following for loop:

For B = 1 To 10
 TextWindow.WriteLine(B)
EndFor

In our code, we assign the values 1 through 10 to the variable B, one at a time, as the loop is executed. An integer is a whole number (such as 3 or 5). An increment is a distinct increase in amount. Incrementing is to distinctly increase a number. “1 To 10” above was incrementing an integer. But since we assigned a variable (“B”), we were technically “incrementing a variable.” And so, we utilized a For Loop to increment a variable. 

298.        <Template-blank & Note>

CLOSING YOUR LOOP

If we create a loop and don’t close the loop, the code will continue on forever. Here’s an example:

Write and execute the following code:

Begin:
A = 50
If A > 25 Then
 TextWindow.WriteLine("50 is more than 25!")
 Goto Begin
EndIf

You will see that when this program is executed, the computer just continues to print "50 is more than 25!" to the screen until you close the window. This is because the condition statement in your loop ("If A > 25") is always true, so the loop always returns to the beginning and does another iteration. This is called an "infinite loop"; under certain circumstances this can lock up a computer and require the shutdown and restart of the computer in order to stop the loop.

To close the loop in our example, you would simply get rid of the “Begin:" label and the “Goto" statement. 

299.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Write a program that includes the following:

-A For Loop, and
-A While Loop.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 
</p>
<p>^G^ SUBMODULE D. The Graphics Window</p>
<p>
300.        <Template-blank & Note>

COUNTING EVEN NUMBERS

Now, let’s make a program – using a For Loop – that counts out only even numbers up to 30.

Write and execute the following code:

For B = 2 To 30 Step 2
 TextWindow.WriteLine(B)
EndFor

“Step” in your code counts up or down depending on the values you assign.

301.        <Template-blank & Note>

COUNTING ODD NUMBERS

So now, let’s reverse the countdown and use only odd numbers!

Write and execute the following code:

For B = 29 To 1 Step -2
 TextWindow.WriteLine(B)
EndFor

302.        <Template-blank & Note>

LOOPS AND CONDITIONAL STATEMENTS

It’s interesting to note that every Loop can be translated into a Conditional Statement. For example, we can rewrite our last For Loop as follows:

Write and execute the following code:

B = 29
Start:
TextWindow.WriteLine(B)
B = B - 2
If (0 < B) Then
 Goto Start
EndIf

Actually, fun fact: every time you write a While Loop in your code, the computer automatically converts it to an If Statement with one or more Goto Statements. This is done behind the scenes; you won't see the actual instructions you typed in the editor change. 

303.        <Template-blank & Note>

COMPARING NUMBERS

Let’s do another loop that will find out the larger of two numbers.

Write and execute the following code:

TextWindow.Write("Type in a number: ")
First_Number = TextWindow.ReadNumber()
TextWindow.Write("Type in another number: ")
Second_Number = TextWindow.ReadNumber()
If (First_Number > Second_Number) Then
 Larger = First_Number
 Else
   Larger = Second_Number
EndIf
TextWindow.WriteLine("The larger number is: " + Larger)



304.        <Template-blank & Note>
CHALLENGE:

Write a program that includes the following:

-Create a loop that counts numbers backwards, one number at a time, starting at 100 down to 1, that also includes Program.Delay(100). 

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 

305.        <Template-blank & Note>

GRAPHICS WINDOW

You can customize certain aspects of the Text Window and how it displays. We touched upon this earlier with foreground color and background color. 

There is also a graphics window. Graphics are pictures displayed on a computer. Graphics are art created on a computer by a person.  

Like the Text Window that displays text, Small Basic also has a Graphics Window for graphics. 

Enter and execute the following code:
GraphicsWindow.Show()

<img src="cid:Image_0.png" />

That’s what the window looks like. 

306.        <Template-blank>

CUSTOMIZING THE WINDOW

Now, to customize the Graphics Window, there are some things you can do.

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.Height = 500
GraphicsWindow.Width = 700
GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "Silver"
GraphicsWindow.Title = "The Graphics Window!"
GraphicsWindow.Show()

307.        <Template-blank & Note>

DRAWING LINES

One of the cool things about the Graphics Window is the ability to draw lines. 

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.DrawLine(10,10,200,10)
GraphicsWindow.DrawLine(10,10,10,200)
GraphicsWindow.DrawLine(10,200,200,200)
GraphicsWindow.DrawLine(200,10,200,200)

Each line of code drew one side of the square. The X Coordinate refers to how far left to right (horizontally) something extends on a grid or a map. The Y Coordinate refers to how far top to bottom (vertically) something extends. Here’s how each number in each line of code laid this out:

●        The first number tells the computer how far left or right the line will be started (called the X Coordinate).
●        The second number tells us where the line starts – up and down – (called the Y Coordinate).
●        The third number tells the computer where the bottom of the line ends right to left.
●        The fourth number tells the computer where the bottom of the line (up and down) ends up.

308.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Draw an X shape using GraphicsWindow.DrawLine.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 

309.        <Template-blank & Note>

LINE THICKNESS:

We can also change the color and thickness of the line. Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.Height = 500</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.Width = 500</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "Silver"</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.Title = "The Colored Square!"</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "Red"</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.DrawLine(10,10,450,10)</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.PenWidth = 10</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "Blue"</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.DrawLine(10,10,10,450)</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.PenWidth = 20</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "Yellow"</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.DrawLine(10,450,450,450)</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.PenWidth = 30</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "Green"</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.DrawLine(450,10,450,450)</p>
<p>^G^ GraphicsWindow.PenWidth = 40</p>
<p>

310.        <Template-blank & Note>

LOOPS AND THE GRAPHICS WINDOW

We can also utilize a Loop with the Graphics Window. 

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.Title = "Growing Lines!"
GraphicsWindow.Height = 500
GraphicsWindow.Width = 500
GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "Red"
GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "Blue"
For A = 1 To 15
 GraphicsWindow.PenWidth = A
 GraphicsWindow.DrawLine(20, A * 20, 400, A * 20)
EndFor

As you can see, we used a For Loop to gradually increase the thickness of the lines.

311.        <Template-blank & Note>

PIXELS

We can also draw pixels in the Graphics Window.

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.SetPixel(20, 20, "Black")

If you can see it, there’s a tiny black dot on the screen. The numbers give the X and Y coordinate for the pixel.

312.        <Template-blank & Note>

TEXT

And in case you were wondering, we can also add text to the Graphics Window.

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.DrawBoundText(70, 70, 150, "John")
GraphicsWindow.DrawBoundText(120, 70, 150, "Sally")
GraphicsWindow.DrawBoundText(180, 70, 150, "Bill")
GraphicsWindow.DrawBoundText(250, 70, 150, "Jessica")
GraphicsWindow.DrawBoundText(70, 120, 150, "John")
GraphicsWindow.DrawBoundText(120, 120, 150, "Sally")
GraphicsWindow.DrawBoundText(180, 120, 150, "Bill")
GraphicsWindow.DrawBoundText(250, 120, 150, "Jessica")

The first number gives the X Coordinate, the second number the Y Coordinate and the third number the size of the font. 

313.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Write a program that includes the following:

-GraphicsWindow.Height, 
-GraphicsWindow.Width, 
-GraphicsWindow.DrawLine,
-GraphicsWindow.PenWidth, 
-GraphicsWindow.PenColor, 
-GraphicsWindow.SetPixel,
-GraphicsWindow.DrawBoundText with multiple font sizes, and
-GraphicsWindow.FontItalic.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com </p>

<p>314. <MCSA>
        1) A ______________ is a construct used to store data that may change as the computer performs its tasks. </p>
~~Variable CORRECT
~~Constant
~~Number
~~Statement
<p>2) In Small Basic, the Read() operation instructs the computer to:</p>
~~Read the entire program and make sure there are no typos.
~~Wait for a response from the user and use that data for something. CORRECT
~~Take the decimal provided and round down to the closest integer.
~~Turn the background of the text editor red.

<p>3) Which of the following symbols is not used in comparison instructions?</p>
~~>
$$$<
~~>=
~~* CORRECT

<p>4) The __ Coordinate tells the computer how far left or right the line will be started. The ____ Coordinate tells the computer how far up or down the line will be started.</p>
~~X, Y CORRECT
~~Y, X
~~T1, T2
~~Left, Right
        
<p>
315.        <Learning Objectives -  Transition List>
</p>
~~^G^ How to assign variables
~~^G^ Performed math equations through coding
~~^G^ Wrote and executed conditional statements
~~^G^ Wrote and executed loops 
~~^G^ Utilized and customized the Graphics Window in Small Basics##EndBull


<p>^G^ <Learning Objectives List, 1.5-second interval></p>
<p>^G^ MODULE 8. Creating Computer Programs</p>
<p>^G^ Learning objectives: </p>
~~^G^ Create subroutines
~~^G^ Commenting code
~~^G^ Write and execute for loops
~~^G^ Create and run subprograms
~~^G^ Develop arrays
~~^G^ Write basic computer programs in Small Basic##EndBull

<p>^G^ SUBMODULE A. Subroutines and Commenting Code  </p>
<p>
SHAPES        <Template-blank>

We can also paint and create shapes in the Graphics Window.

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.BrushColor = "Green"
GraphicsWindow.FillTriangle(300,150,150,300,450,300)

For a triangle we need six numbers. The first two indicate where the top of the triangle is placed (left to right, up to down). The second two indicate the left-hand corner and the third set indicates the right-hand corner. 

316.        <Template-blank & Note>

OTHER SHAPES

You can also draw and paint: squares, rectangles and ellipses (ovals). To draw a circle, you would use the eclipse operation. 

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.Width = 300
GraphicsWindow.Height = 300
GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "Black"
GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "Yellow"
GraphicsWindow.PenWidth = 20
GraphicsWindow.DrawEllipse(50, 50, 200, 200)

317.        <Template-blank & Note>

FILL THE CIRCLE

If you want to fill in the circle so that it looks like a sun, simply change your code.

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.Width = 300
GraphicsWindow.Height = 300
GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "Black"
GraphicsWindow.BrushColor = "Yellow"
GraphicsWindow.FillEllipse(50, 50, 200, 200)

318.        <Template-blank>

CREATING A CIRCLE WITH VARIABLES

Now let’s make a circle using variables.

Write and execute the following code:

A = 20
B = 50
GraphicsWindow.FillEllipse(A, B, 350, 350)

319.        <Template-blank>

MOVING SHAPES

You can also animate shapes and move them around.

Write and execute the following code:

Triangle = Shapes.AddTriangle(50, 100, 100, 50, 150, 100)
Program.Delay(1000)
Shapes.Animate(Triangle, 200, 200, 1000)

The first thing we must include in the parentheses is the name of the shape, followed by x coordinate, y coordinate and then the speed of the move. 

320.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Write a program that includes the following:

-GraphicsWindow.BrushColor, 
-GraphicsWindow.DrawEllipse,
-GraphicsWindow.FillEllipse,
-GraphicsWindow.FillTriangle,
-GraphicsWindow.FillRectangle,
-Shapes.AddTriangle, and
-Shapes.Animate.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 

321.        <Template-blank & Note>

SUBROUTINES

A subroutine is a set of computer instructions, to be used by a main computer program, that performs some task that you may want to do over and over again at various times. The main computer program could do some of its own actions in a specific sequence, then ask the subroutine to do its tasks, and then continue on where it was before it asked the subroutine to do its tasks. Another term for this is a subprogram (a term we discussed earlier in this course).

EXAMPLE: Within a computer program used to operate a college, there could be a subprogram that checked to see if any new students had been enrolled since you last used the program. The main program could use that subprogram as it was starting up, get the data on any new students, and then continue on with its primary functions.

To “call” means to demand or direct something. In normal English this could be used like, “This calls for celebration!” In computers, a call is a direction by a main computer program to execute the tasks of a subprogram. More specifically, when a “call” is made, a program temporarily transfers control of the computer to a subprogram. Once the subprogram is done executing, control of the computer is returned to the main program. A program could make many “calls” to multiple subprograms as the program does its sequence of tasks.  

EXAMPLE: If you were using a video game program, the video game program could call a “high score” subprogram after every game ended.

322.        <Template-blank>

SUBROUTINES

In Small Basic, the name of a subroutine is preceded with the statement "Sub". The instructions that make up the subroutine end off with the statement "EndSub". 

Write and execute the following code:

TextWindow.Write("What is your name?: ")
Name = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("Hi there, " + Name + "! What time do you think it is? ")
Time = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("Well " + Name + ", per your computer, the time now is actually: ")
PrintTime()
Sub PrintTime
 TextWindow.WriteLine(Clock.Time)
EndSub

You execute a subroutine by calling the subroutine name followed by (). The parentheses tell the computer that the main program wants a subroutine executed. 

323.        <Template-blank>

COMMENTS

In a larger program, subroutines become quite useful and save you from writing extra code because you can call the subroutine from anywhere in the program. 

Subroutines can also be used to break apart larger problems into smaller problems. 

An important thing to keep in mind in writing code is the readability of your code. I.e. If another developer takes over after you, they need to know the purpose of different sections of your code. To clarify our code, we use “comments.” For example: PrintTime() 'this is a subroutine that prints the current time

This is called “commenting your code.” 

In Small Basic, comments are preceded with an apostrophe (‘). Comments are ignored by the computer and not executed. 

324.        <Template-blank>

COMMENTS

To comment the code we wrote above, we would do the following:

TextWindow.Write("What is your name?: ") 'This allows the user to enter their name
Name = TextWindow.Read() 'This assigns what the user types to the variable Name
TextWindow.Write("Hi there, " + Name + "! What time do you think it is? ") 'This prints text and allows the user to guess the time
Time = TextWindow.Read() 'This assigns what the user types to the variable Time
TextWindow.Write("Well " + Name + ", per your computer, the time now is actually: ") 'This prints text 
PrintTime() 'This names the subroutine 
Sub PrintTime 'This starts the subroutine
 TextWindow.WriteLine(Clock.Time) 'This accesses the computer's clock and returns the time 
EndSub 'This ends the subroutine

325.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Write your own program that includes a subroutine, and comment your code. 

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 
</p>
<p>^G^ SUBMODULE B. Loops, Subprograms and Arrays </p>

<p>326.        <Template-blank></p>
<p>
TURTLES

Write and execute the following code:

Turtle.Show()

We bet the name of this section makes sense now!

327.        <Template-blank>

MOVING TURTLES

You can move the turtle by entering in numbers inside parentheses (1 means that the Turtle moves 1 pixel; Turtle.Move(50) means that the turtle moves 50 pixels). 

Write and execute the following code:

Turtle.Move(50)
Program.Delay(500)
Turtle.Move(25)
Program.Delay(500)
Turtle.Move(75)
Program.Delay(500)
Turtle.Move(35)
Program.Delay(500)

328.        <Template-blank>

TURTLE TRIANGLE

Now let’s have the turtle draw a triangle.

Write and execute the following code:

Turtle.Angle = 45
Turtle.Move(150)
Turtle.Angle = 135
Turtle.Move(150)
Turtle.Angle = 270

329.        <Template-blank>

COLORFUL TURTLE

We can also have him turn right or left and change the colors. We will now make a rectangle with the turtle.

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "LightYellow" 
GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "Magenta"
Turtle.Move(100)
Turtle.TurnRight()
Turtle.Move(200)
Turtle.TurnRight()
Turtle.Move(100)
Turtle.TurnRight()
Turtle.Move(200)

330.        <Template-blank>

TURTLE FOR LOOP

We can also draw shapes using a for loop. Let’s do an octagon.

Write and execute the following code:

For X = 1 To 8
 Turtle.Move(75)
 Turtle.Turn(45)
EndFor

331.        <Template-blank>

RAINBOW TURTLE

Let’s make a shape that’s virtually a circle. We will also use the X and Y Coordinates to place the turtle where we want it in the Graphics Window. And, to make it more fun, let’s randomize some colors! It’s about to get trippy…

Write and execute the following code:

Turtle.X = 20
Turtle.Y = 200
Sides = 200
Angle = 360 / Sides
Size = 1000 / Sides
For A = 1 To Sides
 GraphicsWindow.PenColor = GraphicsWindow.GetRandomColor()
 GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = GraphicsWindow.GetRandomColor()
 Turtle.Move(Size)
 Turtle.Turn(Angle)
EndFor

332.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Using what you learned so far, have the turtle make a square using a For Loop. Additionally, have a background color, a pen color and try to make the square as centered as you can.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 

333.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:
        
Write a program that includes the following:

-Turtle.Show,
-Turtle.Move,
-Turtle.TurnRight,
-Turtle.Angle,
-Turtle.TurnLeft, and
-Turtle.MoveTo.

334.        <Template-blank & Note></p>

<p>VIDEOS</p>

<p>At this point in the course, we are going to take a short break from Small Basic to cover some additional software development concepts that relate to the code you’ve been writing and your future career as a software developer.</p>
<p>
335. </p>

<p>Watch the following video in full:</p>
<p>VIDEO~~How to Think Like a Developer~~https://drive.google.com/open?id=1PgKRUy734uigbHidgMA7V6evUAxkyZcl
</p>

<p>336.</p>

QUIZ:
~~The CPU can do _____ instructions at a time.
~~1 Billion
~~Five
~~One CORRECT
~~As many as necessary
~~Which of the following is not one of the five elements of a computer program?
~~Entrance
~~Variables
~~Control/Branching
~~Clock CORRECT


<p>337.</p>

<p>Watch the following video in full:</p>
<p>VIDEO~~Using Flow Charts as a Developer~~https://ttamediaservices-uswe.streaming.media.azure.net/3d1ff6a5-d59a-44e7-89e7-595ad8c7cb6b/2018%20Flowcharts.mp4
</p>

<p>338.</p>

QUIZ:
~~__________ are diagrams used to represent algorithms, workflows, or processes.
~~Flowcharts
~~Event driven process chains
~~Family trees
~~Activity diagrams
~~In a flowchart, the parallelogram shape represents:
~~Data entry or display CORRECT
~~Start/End
~~Variables 
~~Operations


<p>339. </p>

<p>Watch the following video in full:</p>
<p>VIDEO~~Troubleshooting~~https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Aga6YEJ_XhMfBcn6oRirtuV2VZtGKyXE/view?usp=sharing
</p>

<p>340. </p>

QUIZ:
~~Troubleshooting can be defined as:
~~Identifying the problem in a system or program. CORRECT
~~Deleting any code that you think is unimportant.
~~Uploading your code to the web.
~~Locating the person who originally wrote the code you are dealing with.
~~What is the name of the troubleshooting approach explained in the previous video?
~~The bottom-up approach
~~The half-split approach CORRECT
~~The move-the-problem approach
~~The follow-the-path approach

<p>341.</p>

<p>Watch the following video in full:</p>
<p>VIDEO~~Breaking Down a Program~~https://drive.google.com/file/d/1jlJue1RYRHz2X7b-1snc-7KCfrdBS28c/view?usp=sharing
</p>

<p>342.</p>

QUIZ:
~~When creating a computer program, you should:
~~Build the whole program from start to finish in one sitting.
~~Break the program up into “bite size” pieces and build one step at a time. CORRECT
~~Start from the end and work your way backwards.
~~Not troubleshoot your code as you write it.
~~

<p>343.</p>

<p>Watch the following video in full:</p>

<p>VIDEO~~How to do Your Job as a Developer~~https://drive.google.com/file/d/18cXSkclJbeBjot6MR7B0-t_5I6NyetgG/view?usp=sharing
</p>

<p>344.</p>

QUIZ:

~~If you run into issues when building your program, which of these should you NOT use to find a solution?
~~Stack Overflow
~~Google
~~Dotnetpearls.com
~~Facebook CORRECT
~~Where can you find the official documentation for Microsoft technologies?
~~Microsoft Developer Network CORRECT
~~Stack Overflow
~~GitHub
~~The Linux Documentation Project


<p>345. </p>

<p>MORE SUBROUTINES

We can also use subroutines to handle variables.

Write and execute the following code:

TextWindow.Write("Type a number: ")
Number_1 = TextWindow.ReadNumber()
TextWindow.Write("Type another number: ")
Number_2 = TextWindow.ReadNumber()
TextWindow.Write("Let's type another number: ")
Number_3 = TextWindow.ReadNumber()
TextWindow.Write("And one last number: ")
Number_4 = TextWindow.ReadNumber()
Largest_Number()
TextWindow.WriteLine("The largest number is: " + Largest_Number)
Sub Largest_Number
If Number_1 > (Number_2 + Number_3 + Number_4) Then
Largest_Number = Number_1
ElseIf Number_2 > (Number_1 + Number_3 + Number_4) Then
Largest_Number = Number_2
ElseIf Number_3 > (Number_1 + Number_2 + Number_4) Then
Largest_Number = Number_3
Else
Largest_Number = Number_4
EndIf
EndSub

346.        <Template-blank & Note>

SUBPROGRAM

Now let’s try another subprogram that will be called three times.

Write and execute the following subprogram:

TextWindow.BackgroundColor = "DarkRed"
TextWindow.Write("This is a program that allows you to choose from various sounds you'd wish to hear. You'll get to choose three times! ")
Sound()
Sub Sound
Start:
TextWindow.Write("To hear a bell ring, type Bell. To hear a chime, type Chime. To hear a click sound, type Click: ")
Sound_Choice = TextWindow.Read()
 If Sound_Choice = "Bell" Then 
   Sound.PlayBellRing()
 ElseIf Sound_Choice = "Chime" Then
   Sound.PlayChime()
 ElseIf Sound_Choice = "Click" Then
   Sound.PlayClick()
   Else 
     TextWindow.Write("Please type Chime, Bell or Click.")
     Goto Start
 EndIf 
EndSub
Sound()
Sound()

347.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Create a subroutine that includes variables.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 

348.        <Template-blank & Note>

ARRAYS
        
An array is a collection of data, arranged in rows and columns. In computers, an array is a group of related things that are stored together in a sequence. It is a way things can be organized in a computer in a logical way. Arrays can be quite simple, or quite complex.

EXAMPLE: A simple array would be something like the numbers 7, 3 and 15. It would be written out like this:

[7,3,15]

These three pieces of data are called elements – they are the elements of the array.

A system is needed for identifying each element of an array. The simplest method for this is to start numbering them at zero starting at the left position and count up from there. 

In the above example, the element "7" would be at position 0, "3" would be at position 1 and "15" would be at position 2.

Another word for the position of an element is the "index" of the element – for the above example of an array, index 0 is "7", index 1 is "3", etc. The plural form if "index" is "indices", pronounced "IN-dih-sees".

Each element, therefore, has two properties: its index and its value.

EXAMPLE: You have three pictures of your cat and you could save them in an array: CatPic1, CatPic2 and CatPic3. Here, index 1 has a value of "CatPic2".

In some computer languages, including SmallBasic, the index for an element in an array can be a unique text item, instead of a number.

Example: 

You could have an array with three elements: 4, 22, 8

The indices for these elements could be:

"planes"
"trains"
"automobiles"

Here, the element in the array with the index "trains" would have a value of 22.

349.        <Template-blank & Note>
</p>
<p>^G^ SUBMODULE C. Working with Data Structures</p>
<p>
ARRAYS

Write and execute the following code:

TextWindow.Write("Enter the name for User 1: ")
User_1_Name = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("How old is User 1?: ")
User_1_Age = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("Enter the name for User 2: ")
User_2_Name = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("How old is User 2?: ")
User_2_Age = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("Enter the name for User 3: ")
User_3_Name = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("How old is User 3?: ")
User_3_Age = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("Enter the name for User 4: ")
User_4_Name = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("How old is User 4?: ")
User_4_Age = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("Greetings Users! ")
TextWindow.Write(User_1_Name + ", you are " + User_1_Age + " years old! ")
TextWindow.Write(User_2_Name + ", you are " + User_2_Age + " years old! ")
TextWindow.Write(User_3_Name + ", you are " + User_3_Age + " years old! ")
TextWindow.Write(User_4_Name + ", you are " + User_4_Age + " years old! ")

We can utilize an array to replace having to create the variables User_1_Name, User_1_Age, User_2_Name, User_2_Age, User_3_Name, User_3_Age, User_4_Name and User_4_Age. Instead we can use an index to store the names and ages. 

Each of these are indices for the array and are stored as one variable. Storing values in an array allows you to access arrays inside of loops. 

350.        <Template-blank & Note>

ARRAYS

Now, let’s change the code you just wrote into an array.

Write and execute the following code:

For A = 1 To 4
 TextWindow.WriteLine("Please enter the name for User " + A + ":")
 Name[A] = TextWindow.Read()
EndFor
For B = 1 To 4
 TextWindow.WriteLine("What is User " + B + "'s age?:")
 Age[B] = TextWindow.Read() 
EndFor
TextWindow.Write("Hello ")
For A = 1 To 4
 TextWindow.Write(Name[A])
 If A < 3 Then
   TextWindow.Write(", ")
 ElseIf A < 4 Then
   TextWindow.Write(" and ")
 EndIf
EndFor 
TextWindow.Write(". You are ")
For B = 1 To 4
 TextWindow.Write(Age[B])
 If B < 3 Then
   TextWindow.Write(", ")
 ElseIf B < 4 Then
   TextWindow.Write(" and ")
   Else 
     TextWindow.Write(" respectively.")
 EndIf 
EndFor
TextWindow.WriteLine("")

In the above code, “A” and “B” are referred to as the operators. Our indices are 1 to 4 and visually would look something like this:
                                                
</p>
<p>Indices</p><p>1</p><p>2</p><p>3</p><p>4</p><p>A</p><p>(Name)</p><p>Name entered by user</p><p>Name entered by user</p><p>Name entered by user</p><p>Name entered by user</p><p>B</p><p>(Age)</p><p>Age entered by user</p><p>Age</p><p>entered by user</p><p>Age</p><p>entered by user</p><p>Age</p><p>entered by user</p>
<p>
351.        <Template-blank & Note>

ARRAYS

Let’s write another array.

Write and execute the following code:

TextWindow.Write("What is your name?: ")
Input["Name"] = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("How tall are you?: ")
Input["Height"] = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("What year were you born?: ")
Input["Birth_year"] = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("What is your favorite color?: ")
Input["Color"] = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("What country were you born in?: ")
Input["Country"] = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.Write("Please type one of the following to pull relevant data: Name, Height, Birth_year, Color or Country. ")
Index = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.WriteLine("The " + Index + " you entered is " + Input[Index] + "!")

352.        <Template-blank & Note>

DATA STRUCTURES

To fully understand arrays, you must know what a “data structure” is. A data structure refers to the organization of related pieces of information. There are different data structures that each allow different operations to be performed on the data.  A data structure refers to how the data is organized in terms of implementation (use of the data; relation of the various parts of the data). It is a particular way to organize data in a computer so that it can be used efficiently.

Data structures are used as a means of organizing information in a computer so that the data can be utilized in an efficient manner. 

EXAMPLE: Consider two different areas of business: The shipping industry and the manufacturing industry.

The types of data the shipping industry may need to collect and organize will center around vehicles and their capacity, shipping rates, fuel costs, travel times between various geographical points, etc.

The types of data the manufacturing industry may need to collect and organize will center around raw materials, product manufacturing methods and times, inventory locations and amounts, shipping information, etc.

The structure of the data used by computers in these two industries may have similarities, but it’s certain that the data structures won’t be identical.

A linear data structure is simply a data structure where the data in the structure are organized one after the other – basically, a list. 

EXAMPLE: A list of the states in the U.S. Each element of the structure, conceptually, comes right before or after another element.

When speaking about arrays, “dimension” has a specific meaning. A one-dimensional array is a linear data structure. The last program we wrote was a one-dimensional array. 

A two-dimensional array is basically an array of arrays. Essentially, you could think of this as a grid of rows and columns, where each entry in the grid is itself an array. You will explore this in the next section.

353.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Create your own one-dimensional array.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        A
cademy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 

354.        <Template-blank & Note>

TWO-DIMENSIONAL ARRAYS
        
We will now write a two-dimensional array. 

Write and execute the following code:

Animals["Princess"]["Color"] = "Black"
Animals["Princess"]["Species"] = "Dog
Animals["Ivy"]["Color"] = "Gray with dark spots and stripes"
Animals["Ivy"]["Species"] = "Cat"
Animals["Goldie"]["Color"] = "Gold"
Animals["Goldie"]["Species"] = "Fish"
Animals["Tweet"]["Color"] = "Green with yellow"
Animals["Tweet"]["Species"] = "Bird"
TextWindow.Write("What is the name?: ")
Name = TextWindow.Read()
TextWindow.WriteLine("Their color is: " + Animals[Name]["Color"])
TextWindow.WriteLine("Their species is: " + Animals[Name]["Species"])

When the program runs, it will ask you for the name of the pet. Enter one of the four names (Princess, Ivy, Goldie or Tweet).

Visually, this is what we created in our array:

</p>
<p>Name:</p><p>Princess</p><p>Ivy</p><p>Goldie</p><p>  Tweet</p><p>Color:</p><p>Black</p><p>  Gray with dark spots and stripes</p><p>Gold</p><p>   Green with yellow</p><p>Species:</p><p>Dog</p><p>Cat</p><p>Goldfish</p><p>Parakeet</p>
<p>
355.        <Template-blank & Note>

GRAPHICS AND ARRAYS 

Arrays can also be used with Graphics.

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "Black"
GraphicsWindow.Height = 600
GraphicsWindow.Width = 605
Rows = 10
Columns = 10
Sides = 50
For A = 1 To Columns
 For B = 1 To Rows
   GraphicsWindow.BrushColor = "Blue"
   Squares[A][B] = Shapes.AddRectangle(Sides, Sides)
   Shapes.Move(Squares[A][B], A * Sides, B * Sides)
 EndFor
EndFor

356.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Create your own two-dimensional array.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com </p>

<p>SUBMODULE D. Putting it all together

357.        <Template-blank>

SOME BASIC PROGRAMS

Now we will put together some of what you’ve learned so far to make some basic programs. Actually type out all code in the Editor – this is vital experience for you as a developer. 

358.        <Template-blank>

PROGRAM 1

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "LightCyan"
GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "DarkSlateBlue"
GraphicsWindow.Width = 400
GraphicsWindow.Height = 400
For A = 1 To 200 Step 6
 GraphicsWindow.DrawRectangle(200 - A, 200 - A, A * 2, A * 2)
 Program.Delay(100)
 EndFor
For A = 1 To 200 Step 6
 GraphicsWindow.DrawEllipse(200 - A, 200 - A, A * 2, A *2)
 Program.Delay(100)
EndFor

Look over your code and try to see what each line does exactly.

359.        <Template-blank>

PROGRAM 2

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.Width = 1000
GraphicsWindow.Height = 650
GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "Black"
A = 1000
B = 1000
For C = 1 To 100000
 D = Math.GetRandomNumber(3)
 E = 500
 Program.Delay(.1)
 F = 30
 If (D = 1) then
   E = 30
   Program.Delay(.1)
   F = 1000
 EndIf
 If (D = 2) Then
   E = 1000
   F = 1000
   Program.Delay(.1)
 EndIf
 A = (A + E) / 2
 Program.Delay(.1)
 B = (B + F) / 2
 Random_Color = GraphicsWindow.GetRandomColor()
 GraphicsWindow.SetPixel(A, B, Random_Color)
EndFor

Look over your code and try to see what each line does exactly.

360.        <Template-blank >

PROGRAM 3

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.Title = "America!"
GraphicsWindow.Width = 1000
GraphicsWindow.Height = 600
For A = 1 To 100000
 GraphicsWindow.BrushColor = "Red"
 B = Math.GetRandomNumber(1000)
 C = Math.GetRandomNumber(1000)
 GraphicsWindow.FillEllipse(B, C, 4, 4)
EndFor
For D = 1 To 100000
 GraphicsWindow.BrushColor = "Blue"
 B = Math.GetRandomNumber(500)
 C = Math.GetRandomNumber(275)
 GraphicsWindow.FillEllipse(B, C, 4, 4)
EndFor

Look over your code and try to see what each line does exactly.

361.        <Template-blank>

PROGRAM 4

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.Width = 275
Turtle.X = 130
Turtle.Y = 400
GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "Green"
Turtle.Move(150)
Turtle.X = 135
Turtle.Y = 400
GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "Green"
Turtle.Move(150)
Turtle.X = 100
Turtle.Y = 200
GraphicsWindow.PenColor = "MediumVioletRed"
Turns = 200
Length = 300 /  Turns
Angle = 400 / Turns
Turtle.Speed = 10
For A = 1 To 6
 For B = 1 To Turns
   Turtle.Move(Length)
   Turtle.Turn(Angle)
 EndFor
 Turtle.Turn(18)
EndFor
Turtle.X = 128.5
Turtle.Y = 193

Look over your code and try to see what each line does exactly.

362.        <Template-blank>

PROGRAM 5

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "DarkBlue"
GraphicsWindow.Height = 600
GraphicsWindow.Width = 605
Rows = 10
Columns = 10
Sides = 50
For A = 1 To Columns
 For B = 1 To Rows
   GraphicsWindow.BrushColor = GraphicsWindow.GetRandomColor()
   Squares[A][B] = Shapes.AddRectangle(Sides, Sides)
   Shapes.Move(Squares[A][B], A * Sides, B * Sides)
 EndFor
EndFor
For A = 1 To Columns
 For B = 1 To Rows
   Shapes.Animate(Squares[B][A], 300, 0, 1000)
   Program.Delay(50)
 EndFor
EndFor
For A = 1 To Columns
 For B = 1 To Rows
   Shapes.Animate(Squares[B][A], 288, 500, 1000)
   Program.Delay(10)
 EndFor
EndFor
For A = 1 To Columns
 For B = 1 To Rows
   Shapes.Animate(Squares[B][A], 275, 250, 1000)
   Program.Delay(10)
 EndFor
EndFor

Look over your code and try to see what each line does exactly.

363.        <Template-blank>

EVENTS

An event is an action or something that occurs that is detected by a computer program. There can be system events (events that occur as a result of operations the computer does automatically), or user events, like typing on the keyboard or clicking a mouse. 

In Small Basic, an event is something that reacts to a user’s action and is when the computer tells you that something interesting has happened. For example, if you make a program that turns the screen blue when you click on the word “blue,” clicking on the word "blue" would be the event. 

Events can make programs more interesting and interactive. 

Interactive means that two things influence one another and create effects on each other. In computers, interactive refers to a computer that is able to be communicated with and gotten to perform activities by a human; these activities involve the person using the computer. An interactive computer is a computer that you can affect in some way (move a pointer on a screen and select something, etc.) and which will respond in some manner.  Most, if not all, computers you’ve handled have been interactive.

The computer game "Hangman" could be developed in Small Basic and would include events. In this game, the user makes choices and the program receives the user’s input using events. 

There is such a thing as “event-driven programming.” This is programming where the flow of the program is controlled by events. An example would be a program in which the program flow is determined by the typing of keys and clicking the mouse.  

364.        <Template-blank>

FLICKR

Flickr is a website where people can store and display images. 
We will now use the MouseDown event in the following program (you will see what it does when you run the program). We can pull a picture from Flickr!

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.Title = "It's raining cats and dogs!"
GraphicsWindow.Width = 700
GraphicsWindow.Height = 700
GraphicsWindow.MouseDown = Pics
Sub Pics
 Picture = Flickr.GetRandomPicture("Cats, Dogs")
 GraphicsWindow.DrawResizedImage(Picture, 0, 0, 700, 700)
EndSub

365.        <Template-blank>

DISPLAYING PHOTOS
        
We just used a new operation called “DrawResizedImage” which allows you to display photos. The first word in the parentheses names the picture, the next two numbers are the X and Y Coordinates in the Graphics Window and the last two specify the width and length of the photo (respectively). Let’s get a little tougher on events.

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.DrawBoundText(250, 200, 100, "Click the screen!")
GraphicsWindow.MouseDown = Click
GraphicsWindow.BrushColor = "Yellow"
GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "Black"
Sub Click
 GraphicsWindow.ShowMessage("You clicked the mouse!", "NOTICE")
 A = GraphicsWindow.MouseX - 5
 B = GraphicsWindow.MouseY - 5
GraphicsWindow.FillTriangle(A, B, 30, 30, 40, 40)
EndSub

There are two chunks of text following ShowMessage. The first chunk is what will be displayed inside the window, and the second chunk is what is displayed at the top.

This program contains a subroutine as well. Every time the user clicks in the GraphicsWindow, the subroutine “Click” is called. The Click subroutine results in a couple events: 1. A message pops up and 2. A yellow ray expands out from the top left corner after you shut the message box. One of the unique things about events is that when an event occurs, the subroutine is called automatically. 

In the above code, we assigned the subroutine name to the MouseDown event which is connected to the GraphicsWindow object. Even though the MouseDown looks like a property (attributes of an object), we are actually assigning the subroutine “Click” to it. If MouseDown were a property, we would be assigning it a value (as opposed to a subroutine).

366.        <Template-blank>

PAINT

Now that you are familiar with subroutines, events and other key coding concepts, we can create our very own “Paint” program that will allow you to draw using the mouse. You will be able to draw in rainbow-like colors with a thick brush.

In this next program, we will be using the MouseMove event, which gets the X and Y coordinates, in pixels, of the mouse cursor – based on where it is as compared to the top left of the desktop. 

Write and execute the following code:

GraphicsWindow.MouseMove = A
GraphicsWindow.MouseDown = B
GraphicsWindow.BackgroundColor = "SkyBlue"
GraphicsWindow.PenWidth = (25)
Sub B
 C = GraphicsWindow.MouseX 
 D = GraphicsWindow.MouseY 
EndSub
Sub A
 E = GraphicsWindow.MouseX 
 F = GraphicsWindow.MouseY 
 If (Mouse.IsLeftButtonDown) Then
   GraphicsWindow.PenColor = GraphicsWindow.GetRandomColor()
   GraphicsWindow.DrawLine(C, D, E, F)
 EndIf
C = E
D = F
EndSub
‘Click and hold down mouse as you move it around.

367.        <Template-blank & Note>

CHALLENGE:

Create a program that includes the following events:

-MouseUp, 
-MouseDown,
-MouseMove, 
-KeyDown, and 
-KeyUp.

Email your code from this challenge to a Tech Academy Instructor.

NOTE:
You can use the message system within this LMS, or email an Instructor at:

•        Academy of Learning students:         academyoflearning@learncodinganywhere.com 
</p>
<p>368.     <Template-blank></p>

<p>CONGRATULATIONS! You have reached the end of the Overview of Software Development Course. You have written code and are now familiar with the basics of computer programming. The data you learned on this course, combined with the Computer and Technology Basics Course, will provide a firm tech foundation for your future. </p>

<p>You have two steps remaining on this course:</p>
~~The final essay
~~The final examination##EndBull

<p>369.   <Template-blank & Note>
</p>
<p>ASSIGNMENT:</p>

~~What did you gain from writing code in Small Basic?
~~As a software developer, how can you handle barriers you run into while coding?
~~How can you utilize the data on this course in your future?##EndBull
<p>^G^ <Learning Objectives -  Transition List></p>
~~^G^ Learned how to create subroutines
~~^G^ Learned how to comment code
~~^G^ Wrote and executed for loops
~~^G^ Created and ran subprograms
~~^G^ Developed arrays
~~^G^ Wrote basic computer programs in Small Basic##EndBull

<p>370.    <Final Quiz></p>

<p>FINAL EXAM:</p>
<p>1.        What is a program?</p>
<p>a.        A set of instructions that can be entered into a computer that make it accomplish specific tasks Correct</p>
<p>b.        A piece of hardware that connects to a computer</p>
<p>c.        A tool created to assist the average computer-user</p>
<p>d.        An information processor</p>

<p>2.        What is a variable?</p>
<p>a.        A construct used to store data that may change as the computer performs its tasks Correct</p>
<p>b.        A small program used to perform math functions</p>
<p>c.        A tool used to determine the result of one or more conflicting operations</p>
<p>d.        The main component of a database</p>

<p>3.        What are the five elements of programming?</p>
<p>a.        Entrance point, variables, control/branching, sub-programs and exit point Correct</p>
<p>b.        Entrance point, variables, symbols, statements, and exit point</p>
<p>c.        Entrance point, control/branching, statements, sub-programs, and exit point</p>
<p>d.        Entrance point, control/branching, symbols, statements, and exit point</p>

<p>4.        What is a data structure?</p>
<p>a.        A data format that consists of a prescribed organization of information Correct</p>
<p>b.        Any unique set of characters</p>
<p>c.        A program that determines how data should be arranged</p>
<p>d.        Any arrangement of self-structuring data</p>

<p>5.        What is a data type?</p>
<p>a.        A label given to a piece of data by which a computer can know how the data is to be used Correct</p>
<p>b.        A piece of data that is either variable or constant</p>
<p>c.        A construct used to determine whether or not data has been corrupted</p>
<p>d.        A construct that decides whether or not a certain type of data can be processed</p>

<p>6.        What is a number system? </p>
<p>a.        A system used for writing numbers Correct</p>
<p>b.        A system used for calculations</p>
<p>c.        A system used for keeping track of computer operations</p>
<p>d.        A system used for numbering computer characters</p>

<p>7.        What is ASCII?</p>
<p>a.        A standard that provides a way to represent text characters using numbered codes Correct</p>
<p>b.        An organized set of characters used for encryption of data</p>
<p>c.        A protocol that allows computer programmers to understand user-input</p>
<p>d.        A protocol used decode information</p>

<p>8.        What is unicode? </p>
<p>a.        A standard for representing letters and symbols in computers Correct</p>
<p>b.        A set of code that functions as a single unit</p>
<p>c.        A set of code that is used to create single-page applications</p>
<p>d.        A standard for transmitting data to and from the CPU</p>

<p>9.        What is hexadecimal?</p>
<p>a.        A number system based on 16 digits Correct</p>
<p>b.        A data type that consists of at least 16 decimal points</p>
<p>c.        A binary structure made up of 16 columns</p>
<p>d.        A decimal structure made up of six columns</p>

<p>10.      What is Object-Oriented programming?</p>
<p>a.        An approach to programming that focuses on objects and data Correct</p>
<p>b.        A programming paradigm that relies on CPU efficiency</p>
<p>c.        A style of programming created for the sole purpose of readability</p>
<p>d.        A type of programming intended to replace scripting</p>

<p>11.      What does FIFO stand for?</p>
<p>a.        First in, first out Correct</p>
<p>b.        Fast in, fast out</p>
<p>c.        Frame, image, feature, focus</p>
<p>d.        First iteration, final output</p>

<p>12.      What is the command line?</p>
<p>a.        An interface that allows a user to type commands into a computer Correct</p>
<p>b.        A Integrated Development Environment</p>
<p>c.        A computer programming framework</p>
<p>d.        A program designed to remove unwanted software from a computer</p>

<p>13.      What is a core?</p>
<p>a.        A component of the CPU that processes information Correct</p>
<p>b.        The main component of RAM</p>
<p>c.        The central location of any electronic device</p>
<p>d.        The component in a computer that powers all other components</p>

<p>14.      What is a Framework?</p>
<p>a.        A collection of tools that assist in building software Correct</p>
<p>b.        A preliminary outline of a website or web application</p>
<p>c.       A program used for developing software</p>
<p>d.       A software package that provides stability to applications</p>

<p>15.     What is a file structure? </p>
<p>a.       The manner in which a computer organizes its files Correct</p>
<p>b.       A template by which files are created</p>
<p>c.       The structure of a file</p>
<p>d.       A type of data structure</p>

<p>16.     What is a registry?</p>
<p>a.       A database that stores the settings of the operating system and some applications Correct</p>
<p>b.       A location where users can store information</p>
<p>c.       A location where users can create accounts</p>
<p>d.       A program used to identify data types</p>

<p>17.     Which shape is not used in a flowchart?</p>
<p>a.       Octagon Correct</p>
<p>b.       Parallelogram</p>
<p>c.       Rectangle</p>
<p>d.       Circle</p>

<p>18.     Which of the following is used to write a conditional statement?</p>
<p>a.       if/else Correct</p>
<p>b.       this/that</p>
<p>c.       or/else</p>
<p>d.       if/that</p>

<p>19.     Which of the following is not a sorting algorithm?</p>
<p>a.       Class Correct</p>
<p>b.       Bubble</p>
<p>c.       Insertion</p>
<p>d.       Selection</p>

<p>20.     Which of the following is not a feature of Small Basic?</p>
<p>a.       Accommodates the creation of complex software Correct</p>
<p>b.       Provides smooth transition to other programming languages</p>
<p>c.       Has built-in IDE</p>
<p>D.      Helps teach programming fundamentals</p>